Guide to the Papers on Yale Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Papers on Yale collection
1974-2010
RU 103
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
5.25
.75
The materials consists of essays, dissertations, and articles relating to Yale history.
General note
Forms part of Yale Record Group 49 (YRG 49), Papers and projects on Yale.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The materials were the gift of various individuals and organizations.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Arrangement
The materials are arranged by accession.
Scope and Contents
The materials consists of essays, dissertations, and articles relating to Yale history.
Universities and colleges -- History; Essays; Yale College (1718-1887) -- History; Yale University -- History
- Original collection of papers on Yale, 1974-2001; Accession 19ND-A-251
  - Basagera, Susan, "Women and the Yale University School of Medicine: The first ten years,1916-1926." Includes bibliography. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Gile, Lawrence, "The Yale Peace Council and pacifism at Yale, 1936-1941." 25 p. Includes bibliography., 1977 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Kilpatrick, Donald, "The Emergence of organized athletics in nineteenth century American society: The Yale Experience." 1977. 47 p. Includes bibliography. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Mellen, Henry, "The British invasion of New Haven, 5 July 1779: A study of the heroic town-gown defense of the city." 77 p. Includes bibliography. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Kelly, Kevin J., "Yale men of the 'Rough Riders': Yale spirit in the 'Splendid Little War".' 22 p. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Riendeau, Bradford C.,"In respect to our Southern classmates." 18 p. map, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Luneburg, Thomas R., "Yale and athletics in 1905-1906." 18 p. Includes bibliography., 1977 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Ortel, Erik,"The New Haven riots of 1919." 11 p. map. Includes bibliography., 1978 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Cromwell, Michael S., III, "The lessons of Dwight Hall." 24 p. Includes bibliography. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Kaufman, Robin, "The town-gown riot of 1854: A study of nativism and sectionalanimosities in Yale and New Haven." 35 p. Includes bibliography., 1977 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Heyison, Michael R., "The Conic Sections and Bread and Butter rebellions: Therise of student unity and activism at Yale College from 1825 to 1830." 30 p., 1978 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Smith, Mary Bruce, "Professor Benjamin Silliman: His religion and teaching." 13 p., 1978 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Mirchin, David I, "A composite biography of Yale-in-China bachelors, 1912-1917." 30 p., 1978 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Levine, Harold, "The Yale Daily-News. A study of extracurriculum at Yale." 17 p., 1976 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Green, Steve, "Yale secret societies of the nineteenth century." 15 p., 1976 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Mulrow, Bill, "DKE and the changing nature of Yale fraternities.'', Undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Kohn, Roger S., "Elias Loomis (1811-1889). Pioneer American scientist." 52 p. Includes bibliography., 1979 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Spielman, Eli, "Payne Whitney gymnasium: The calm after the storm." 22 p., 1974 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Baskauskas, Michael, "The Payne Whitney gymnasium: Its development and use." 16 p., 1974 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Kilpatrick, Donald, "Yale's indoor playground. The Payne Whitney gymnasium." 18 p., 1976 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Sundel, Michael, "Yale and New Haven During the Great Depression." 82 p., 1981 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Schulman, Bruce J., "The Reorganization of the Institute of Human Relations at Yale, 1935-1938." 64 p., 1981 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Keehn, Sally, "Passed But Not Forgotten: The Story of the Whiffenpoof Song." 14 p., Undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Green, David, "An Architectural Overview of the Residential Colleges at Harvard and Yale." 176 p., 1981 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Straka, Kathy M. Umbricht, "The Linonian Society Library of Yale College, 1753-1853." 153 p. [Restricted: Permission to copy all or any part must come from author. Author retains all publication rights.], 1981 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Lyon, Richard Abod, "Beatrix Jones Farrand, landscape gardener.", Undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Golden, Richard, 'The Radicalization of Yale College: 1755-1766.'' 96 p. Includes bibliography and bibliographical essay., 1983 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Lampert, David, "Suggestions For a Better Yale: A Compilation of Essays.", 1980 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - O'Connor, Br. Thomas Frederick, "The Yale University Library, 1865-1931." Columbia University Ph.D. Dissertation, 610 p.-- [all rights reserved], 1984 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Sheahan, Sr. Dorothy A., "The Social origins of American Nursing and ItsMovement into the University: A Microcosmic Approach." Ph.D. dissertation, New York University School of Education, Health, Nursing and Arts Professions. 617 p. [Restriction: No photocopying or quotation without permission of the author], 1980 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Condon, Patrick Edward, "Women' s Dormitory." 41 p., 1984 (Box 6, Folder 31)
  - Sabala, Mary, "A History of Alumni Hall." 27 p., 1984 (Box 6, Folder 32)
  - Nickerson, Richard, "From College to University: Yale's Bicentennial Buildings." 43 p., 1984 (Box 6, Folder 33)
  - Chren, Michael, "Bunshaft's Beinecke Library: The Failure of Modernist Aesthetic in Building and Drawing." 21 p., 1984 (Box 6, Folder 34)
  - Catlin, Daniel, Jr., "Liberal Education at Yale: The Yale College Course of Study 1945-1978." Princeton dissertation. 305 p., 1981 (Box 6, Folder 35)
  - Reifenstein, Edward C, "The Master Plans of Yale." 42 p., 1985 (Box 7, Folder 36)
  - Yulo, Christopher,"The Ritter family of stonecutters and their context in 19th century New Haven." 39 p., 1985 (Box 7, Folder 37)
  - Kent, Susan Rodgers, "Hillhouse Avenue: A Study of a Street and the Growth of an Aesthetic.", 1975 (Box 7, Folder 38)
  - Greenberg, David, "Practical Politics in Academia: The Conflicts of the Yale Political Union, 1934-1988." 43 p. (Box 7, Folder 39)
  - Schlanger, Margo, "A Lively Lot of Women, Who Intend to Make Themselves of Use in This World: The Mothers' Club of Lowell House, 1900-1920." 373 p., 1989 (Box 7, Folder 40)
  - Snoke, Albert, "The Yale University School of Nursing, 1956-1967." [RESTRICTED] (Box 8, Folder 41)
  - Transcript of oral history interview with Paul Burnham concerning the use of Educational Testing Service tests at Yale, 1985 (Box 8, Folder 42)
  - Weinberg, Jeremy, "Long Live the King's Yale. How Kingman Brewster's university survived and thrived in the 1960s.", 1992 (Box 8, Folder 43)
  - Johnson, William R, "Letter concerning the history of Furioso .", 1991 (Box 8, Folder 44)
  - Umberger, Willis H, "Lyme and the Yale tradition"(Essay used as basis of presentation to the Class of 1929 luncheon), 1990 September 10 (Box 8, Folder 45)
  - Bockelman, Charles K, "Seven Provosts, 1968-1987", 1997 (Box 8, Folder 46)
  - Somerville, Peter. "Sex Drugs, and Rachmaninoff: Music at Yale in the Late 1960s," 2001. (Box 9, Folder 47)
  - Kilpatrick, Daniel "The Yale Student Body and Admissions Criteria During the 20th Century"., circa 2001 (Box 9, Folder 48)
  - Tercentennial Essays
    - Gottshall, Mary S., "Yale's Role in the War: Preserving the Liberal Arts Education.", 2001 (Box 9, Folder 49)
    - Leineweber, Thomas M., "The Voice of Branzeville An Examination of the Role of the Black Press of Chicago's South Side in the 1030's and 1940s.", 2001 (Box 9, Folder 50)
    - Ahlbrandt, Julia, "The Pope, Martin Luther, and the Vietnam War: How Kingman Brewster and William Sloane Coffin United Yale Against All Odds.", 2001 (Box 9, Folder 51)
    - Mazza, Peter, "Diplomas, Bibles, and Guns The Stories of Four Yale Men in the Civil War.", 2001 (Box 9, Folder 52)
  - Daly, Radley H, "The Secretaries of Yale.", 2002 (Box 9, Folder 53)
  - Horn, Michael Brian, "They Would Not Be Denied: The Yale Unit's Piloting Role in U.S. Military Aviation.", 2002 (Box 9, Folder 54)
- Lecture on the evolution of the American Studies major at Yale, 1953; Accession 19ND-A-466
  - Lecture on the evolution of the American Studies major at Yale, 1953 (Box 1)
- Smith, Suzanne, "History of Yale: 1960-1972", Accession 19ND-A-471
  - Smith, Suzanne, "History of Yale: 1960-1972", 1973 (Box 1)
- Senior essay for the history major, "Entering the Old Boys' Club: The Women of the Yale College Class of 1973 and Factors Affecting Their Entrance into the Professions", 2000; Accession 2000-A-051
  - Senior essay for the history major, "Entering the Old Boys' Club: The Women of the Yale College Class of 1973 and Factors Affecting Their Entrance into the Professions,", 2000 (Box 1)
- "Seventy-five Years of Forestry Education: The Yale University School of Forestry & Environmental Studies, 1900-1975," by George Garrett, Accession 2004-A-050
  - Garrett, George, "Seventy-five Years of Forestry Education: The Yale University School of Forestry & Environmental Studies, 1900-1975," (Box 1)
- Student papers, 1945, 2006; Accession 2006-A-047
  - Furniss, Norman (YC 1945), "Undergraduate Life at Yale, 1820-1830" (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Feinberg, Michael "Team Lux: 10 Years of Yale College Solar Racing - An Analysis", 2006 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Thomas Kaplan, "Yale Has Something to Sell" [computer file], 2010; Accession 2010-A-082; 1
- "The New Haven Free Public Library and the Yale University Press: The New and the Old Create a Perfect Contrast to the New Haven Green" by Michael Harten, 1997; Accession 2014-A-029
  Conditions Governing Access
  The materials are open for research.
  Related Materials
  Related materials are located in RU 554, Yale University Press Records, accession 2013-A-079, Evan's Wing files series.
  - Harten, Michael, "The New Haven Free Public Library and the Yale University Press: The New and the Old Create a Perfect Contrast to the New Haven Green", 1997 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Supplemental architectural drawings and photographs, Undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Supplemental photographs, Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)